Good evening everyone. It's 6 o'clock.
We're going to go ahead and start the
finance committee meeting for February
23rd.
It's a little less daunting than last
time's agenda. So, we're going to kick
it off with temporary resolution 2526
coming through finance. It's
authorization to accept a NOET grant
service safety director. What do you
want to speak to that?
>> Absolutely. Thank you. Uh, this is a
grant that we are able to receive every
single year through NOEC because that is
our energy partner and basically if we
don't use it, we lose it. Um the only
restrictions to use the funds are to
have council approval and to use it
toward energy efficiency within the
city. And so what we've been using the
last few years is we've been using this
money to upgrade lighting throughout all
of the city facilities. So we've done a
lot of lighting in city hall as well as
121 East Chestnut. And so we would like
to continue that this year. Um use those
funds to continue the energy efficient
upgrading of the lights in city hall and
the Chestnut building. And then any
funds that we would have left, uh, we
would just continue to use in other city
properties.
>> Okay. Thank you. Does anyone have any
questions on that?
>> I have three readings. That's okay with
you, Miss Woody. So, I'll be asking for
three readings. Mr. Als be my second.
[snorts] Temporary resolution 20626
coming through water pollution.
Mr. Als is not here. will not be here.
Mr. Ms.jack, are you able to speak to
that?
>> Uh, yes. Thank you, [clears throat] Mr.
Chair. Um, resolution 26-26 is then a
now certificate just essentially uh to
allow the water department to pay for
two AE actoral bills. So, that's all
it's seeking to accomplish and I will be
asking for a suspension and Miss Cohen
will be my second.
>> Okay. Anybody have any questions on that
one?
Temporary resolution 2726 also coming
through water pollution. Mr. Bisjack. Uh
thank you, Mr. Chair. Once again, this
legislation is seeking to move uh
5,98366
here from uh the salary administrative
uh water uh line to the retirement uh
water line item. Uh once again, just to
account for a retirement payout. uh it
was accidentally budgeted in that line
item. So, we just need to move it to
make sure we can pay out that
retirement. Outside of that, I have
nothing else. We'll be going uh the full
three readings unless Darren, you got
anything to the contrary on that?
>> All right. Thank you. Thank you. And
then Miss Cohen will also be my second.
Any questions on that one?
>> And uh temporary resolution 2826 also
coming through water pollution.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. Uh this
resolution seeking uh to allow the
service safety director here to enter
into a contract for the Frederick Street
sewer separation project. Uh the
contracts not to exceed uh $2.8 million.
Uh once again, we will be going through
readings on that and Miss Cohen will be
my second.
>> Okay.
Does anyone have any questions on that
one?
No. All right.
Temporary resolution 3026 that is not
coming through water water pollution.
That is
>> what about 29-26
already checked that one. That's why I
skipped it. Okay. 2926. You have one
more. There you go.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. If I could
invite Curtis to come up and address
this point, please uh for council
>> or Stephen. That works. All right. Thank
you.
>> Yeah. Curtis can certainly feel free to
chime in if there's anything he has to
add, but since I put the legislation
together and have been doing kind of the
grunt work to start on this, I figured
I'd speak. Uh, so this legislation, so
for a little bit of background, uh, we
became aware later last year after that
July flooding event that there was, um,
funding assistance through the NRCS to
um, make stream bank restoration
improvements in areas where uh,
basically they were damaged during a
major storm event. and um infrastructure
is in peril. So uh we
Curtis and my offices sent some folks
out to uh investigate in Euing Run,
Feder's Run. We found that there were uh
four different areas where sanitary
sewer manholes andor pipe were exposed
to the stream and presumed to be because
of that event some erosion that had
occurred. So we had had some initial
discussions, made initial request uh and
they have deemed those areas um eligible
for funding and have allotted funding
for that and um uh in order to move
forward with that we of course have a
variety of paperwork agreements that
will need to be signed and this
legislation here will authorize the
mayor to enter into those agreements
that are necessary for us to receive
that funding. Uh and I think it was
noted I don't know if it was noted but
um the as of now from the numbers I've
been given the they are estimating that
the cost of the improvements will be in
the range of 172,000 and they do cover
75% of that. Uh the way this uh
assistance works is we as the city would
have to put up the money up front, pay
for that cost and then we submit for
reimbursement thereafter and again they
would cover about 75% of that which is
129,000 give or take and we would be on
the hook for the remaining 43,000.
Um I do have some an email into NRCS
that they have not answered at this
point in terms of what happens if the
bids come in higher than that estimate
or we have change orders that that
increase the cost. So, I'm still waiting
to hear word from them on that as to
what those specifics are, but uh again,
that's generally what we're looking at
here. Um and I'm happy to answer any
questions that anybody might have if
there's anything additional.
>> Any questions for Stephen?
>> I have a question, Mr. Chair.
>> Yes.
>> Um now, is is this uh the 75% match or
the reimbursement, is that is this
guaranteed or is there a chance that the
the reimbursement application could be
denied? So yeah, I will say uh what I
have been told is there is a time limit
on the use of the funding. The initial
time limit is 220 days from the
allotment of the um of the assistance.
That a lotment, we were informed of that
in February, which would put the um the
deadline by September. Now, in the
discussions I've had with my local NRCS
contact who I've been working with on
this, he says it is very common for uh
local agencies to receive extensions to
that. Uh and and from the impressions
I've been given, uh it seems like
they're generally understanding that
these projects take time. Uh especially
in this case, we're dealing with permits
through the Army Corps of Engineers,
environmental issues. Um it's going to
be during Indiana bat season, so we may
have to delay to get out of out of the
season for that endangered species to
avoid any issues there. Uh so we're
dealing with some environmental issues
and in general I'm told that they are
understanding and it is common for
extensions to be given but my local guy
did say he can't say it's not up to him
of course he can't say with 100%
certainty that it might not be denied at
some point in the future. Uh again
likely it wouldn't be but again I
certainly can't sit here and say that
that that's not a possibility at least.
I think it's a small chance from what's
been given to me. Uh, but it's it's a
nonzero chance is my understanding.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Any other questions for Stephen?
See none. Good. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you. So, I'll I'll just be clear.
I'll be going for suspension and Miss
Cohen will be my second on that as well.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Now, temporary resolution
3026 coming through finance. This is a
then and now resolution to pay a bill
from A that came through the service
safety director's office. That was for
city street lights. Correct.
>> That is correct.
>> Okay. [clears throat]
Anybody have any questions or opposed to
paying our AP electric bill?
>> I do have a question, Mr. Chair.
>> Sure.
>> Um Carrie, I don't know, you may know
this, maybe you don't. Um I'm
[clears throat] just curious. I see in
the legislation it's asking for 3,000.
Um I'm just curious if if you might know
what the rate of the the the per
kilowatt hour charge that a charges the
city for our energy. Um I'm just curious
if that's information you know or maybe
could obtain.
>> I definitely have that information in
the office. I do not have it memorized,
but I'm more than happy to send that out
to you tomorrow.
>> Thank you so much.
Any other questions?
We're going to do two readings on that.
Mr. Sully will be my second.
Temporary resolution 3126 that's coming
through safety committee. Mr. Bisjack.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Chair. So, yeah, this
is definitely the water and safety
committee night here at council. Um, so
this legislation here is seeking to
appropriate funds from the general fund.
Um, we've got a new assistant fire chief
here, so we need to make sure we have a
uniform for him that reflects that new
rank. Um, and this, uh, legislation is
seeking to, uh, move $4,800 here, um,
from the medical, physical, drugs, fire
line item, uh, to the uniform allowance
line item. So, uh, we will be going, uh,
the full three readings here, and Mr. Og
will be my second on that.
>> Okay, any questions on that one?
Seeing none, that's the end of
resolutions to introduce. We have one
new ordinance, temporary ordinance 426
that's coming through the law committee,
Miss Smiley.
>> Yes, thank you. So speaking of a so they
have been doing work for the city for
the last two years and they need to
request four additional supplemental
easements to complete the work for those
transmission lines and the right-of-way
manager and our city engineer have both
reviewed and approved the designs but
also um they have had an opportunity to
um to approve the proposed rate
calculated on the value of the land
which has been deemed appropriate. And
these four lots are on Logan Lancaster
Road, US 33 and Horns Mill Road and they
are all part of the city's southern
wellfields
and I will be going three readings and
my second is Mr. Carr.
>> Very well. Any questions on that?
>> Very well.
I don't have any additional ordinances.
Do we have any department updates for
finance tonight?
Woody,
>> I used a phone a friend over here. Law
director Hall was able to pull up the AE
invoice. So, Mr. Nisley, Councilman
Eisley, Nisley, sorry, I do have that
answer for you. Thanks to Law Director
Hall. Um, the cost per kilowatt hour is
02890.
>> All right. Thank you. I appreciate that.
Yep.
>> [snorts]
>> Any department updates?
>> Two meetings in a row. The class has
been amazing.
>> All right,
council meeting prep. Mr. Porter,
>> we have nothing outside the regular
order of business as on the agenda. Um,
we will be moving to excuse council
member Als from this evening's meeting,
though.
Okay.
Any other discussion items for finance?
No.
Yikes. All right. I'll take a motion to
adjurnn.
>> So move.
>> And I'm going to second since Mr. Als is
not here. So we are adjourned at 6:12.
>> The shortest one yet. We will commence
the regular meeting of Lancaster City
Council at the published time of 6:30.
The Frankie [music] Smith Funeral Home
and Crematory in Lancaster and the
Johnson Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore
have a long and wonderful history of
serving our community. [music] Feel free
to give us a call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at [music] either of
our two locations, 405 North Columbus
Street in Lancaster and 207 South Main
Street in Baltimore. Respect [music] for
tradition, regard for change.
>> Great automotive service is just around
[music] the corner at the Buckeye family
of dealerships. Whether it's Buckeye
Nissan in Hillyard, Georgeesville Nissan
[music] at the Georgeesville Auto Mall,
Buckeye Honda of Lancaster, Buckeye
Toyota of Lancaster, or Buckeye
Collision Center in Hillyard. Team
Buckeye services all makes and models at
each location, utilizing [music] modern
practices with hundreds of years of
experience, giving you peace of mind.
That's how we Buckeye. [music]
[music]
Rise if able and join me in a moment of
prayer. God grant us the serenity to
accept the things that we cannot change,
the courage to change the things we can,
and lastly and most importantly, the
wisdom to know the difference. Please
join me in the pledge of allegiance.
I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> I call the February 23rd, 2026 Lancaster
City Council meeting to order. Please
call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> Mr. Bisjack
>> here.
>> Mr. Carr
>> here,
>> Miss Cohen [clears throat]
>> Mrs. Hoop here,
>> Mr. Nisley
>> here,
>> Mr. OG
>> Mr. Skunover
>> here,
>> Miss Smiley
>> here, and Mr. Sully
>> here.
>> Let the record reflect that nine members
of Lancaster City Council are present
this evening.
>> Mr. President, like to make a motion
that we excuse Mr. Als.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to um
excuse Council Member Als. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. Reading
and disposing of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes um dated
February 9th, 2026.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We motion a second to receive and file
the journal. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> Now, now we move to the reports of city
officials. I have five of them. I have
email dated February 12th, 2026
regarding homeowner rehabilitation
assistance. Uh submitted by our grants
manager, Michelle McCrady. Email dated
February 12th, 2026 regarding BWC City
of Lancaster employer spotlight winter
2026 edition submitted by service safety
director Carrie Woody. Email dated
February 17, 2026 regarding tree
commission appointments submitted by
Mayor Don McDaniel. Email dated February
19th, 2026 regarding the 2026 CDBG
public notice of funding availability
submitted by our grants manager Michelle
McCrady. And finally, email dated
February 21st, 2026 regarding introduced
temporary resolution
um 28-26 and 29-26 submitted by our
storm water manager, Stevens Wellstead.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the reports of city officials.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Now move
on to communications.
>> I have three of them this evening. I
have e email dated February 11th, 2026
regarding agreements in a draft
agreement submitted by Meg Fur.
A series of emails dated February 18th
and 19th, 2026 regarding public records
request 2021 through 2023 Northeast Gas
main replacement submitted by Mark Zerta
and responded by Curtis Wait. email
dated February 20th, 2026 regarding a
health department annual report
submitted by Joel Ebel with um Fairfield
County Health Commissioner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to receive
and file the communications. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> Special awards and presentations.
>> I have none this evening.
>> Well, I think we do have one. Oh, we do.
>> I I heard it is council member Carr's
birthday this evening. Is that correct?
>> It's correct. And I will uh refrain from
saying which one it is.
>> Now, see, we were going to ask that
question.
>> 28th.
>> It's it's it's a an anniversary of my
28th birthday. There we go. Well,
congratulations and happy birthday.
Thank you for joining us on your
birthday.
>> Uh petitions and memorials.
>> There are no petitions or memorials this
evening. We've now reached the time in
our agenda where we set aside a time for
voters and taxpayers to address council.
Are there any individuals here this
evening who wish to address council?
Seeing none, we thank you for coming. I
have to take the glasses on and off now.
So in order to see and read. So um we
now move on to the reports of standing
committees.
>> I have 11 this evening. I have water
water pollution meeting agenda dated
February 10th, 2026. Submitted by Mr.
Als. Service committee meeting agenda
dated February 10th, 2026 submitted by
Mr. Nisley. Administrative committee
meeting agenda dated February 11th, 2026
submitted by Miss Cohen. Water pollution
meeting revised meeting schedule uh
dated February 11 or February 13th, 2026
submitted by Mr. Als.
Uh, safety committee meeting minutes
dated February 16, 2026, submitted by
Mr. Bishjack. Public works committee
agenda dated February 21st, 2026,
submitted by Mr. Carr and Charles Mullet
with LDA, operations manager.
Law committee meeting agenda dated
February 17, 2026, submitted by Miss
Smiley and Law Director Hall, Stephanie
Hall. Law director Stephanie Hall.
Administrative committee meeting minutes
dated February 19th, 2026. Submitted by
Miss Cohen.
Finance Committee meeting agenda dated
February 20, 2026. D submitted by Mr.
Skoover. Finance Committee meeting
minutes dated February 20th submitted by
2026 submitted by Mr. Skunover. And
finally, public works committee meeting
agenda dated February 23rd, 2026
submitted by Mr. Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to receive and file
the reports of standing committees. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
special committees.
>> There are no reports of special
committees this.
>> Thank you. Public hearings, we have
none. We now move on to the reading of
resolutions. We have no third readings
this evening, but move to second
readings. Beginning with temporary
resolution 1126.
>> I have a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to enter into an
agreement with the Ohio Department of
Transportation to purchase rock salt for
2026 and 2027 winter season. This is
through public works committee. Mr. Carr
and Mr. Sully.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to uh make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the third reading of resolution
uh temporarily numbered 11-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution 1126.
Council member Carr, any discussion on
the motion to suspend?
um only that this is part of a group of
uh pieces of legislation that uh only we
were planned to do two ratings based on
missing the uh uh the meeting due to the
snow.
>> Thank you.
>> Please call the
>> um Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skoonover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes. Motion to suspend the rules and
wave the third reading of temporary
resolution 1126 passes 9 to zero.
Council member Carr.
>> Mr. President, uh um this this is an
annual piece of legislation uh to enter
into uh u purchase agreements with ODOT
on rock salt. I have no further comment
on that other than
>> you you need to make a motion to pass.
[laughter]
>> Sorry, getting still learning here. Um
Mr. President, I'd like to u to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record u or
resolution temporar temporarily numbered
11-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 1126. Any
further comment, council member car? No.
>> No further comment other than this is an
annual piece of legislation to purchase
um salt for the rest.
>> Any further discussion? Please call the
role.
>> Mr. Bisch.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr. Yes,
>> Miss Cohind.
>> Yes,
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Mr. Nisley.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. OG.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Miss Smiley.
>> and Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass engross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
1126 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
resolution 12-26.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter into contracts for the
purchase of chemicals for use by the
division of water. It's through water
water pollution committee. Mr. Bisjack
and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council suspend its rules and wave the
third reading for temporary resolutions
1226 and 13-26.
>> Oh, second. We have a motion and a
second to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
1226 and temporary resolution 1326. Any
further discussion on the motion to
motions to suspend?
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes. Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
12-26
and 13-26
passes 9 to zero. Council member
Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and engross upon the
written record temporary resolution
12-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
12-26.
Any discussion? Council member Bisjack.
>> Uh, nope. This is just allowing the
service safety director to enter into a
contract for purchase of chemicals by
the water department.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes. [clears throat]
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
12-26 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
resolution 13-26.
>> Um, let me read it first.
>> Yes.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter into contract contracts for
the purchase of pipes and fittings for
the use by the division of water is
through water pollution. Mr. Bisjack and
Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
number 13-26.
>> Second.
>> A motion a second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 1326. Any discussion? Council
member Bisjack.
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Any further discussion? Hearing none.
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr?
>> Miss Cohen?
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop?
>> Mr. Nisley?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. OG?
>> Mr. Skunover?
>> Yes.
>> Miss Smiley?
>> Mr. Sully? Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 13-26 passes 9 to0
temporary resolution 14-26.
>> A resolution to amend 2025 appropriation
budgets and amend the certificate of
appropriations
with the county auditor in the escrow
fund 80060
due to partial draw for the northwater
treatment plant replacement project.
This is through finance committee. Mr.
Skunover, Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Skunover. Mr. President,
I'd like to make a motion that council
suspend its rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 1426.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution 1426.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Thanks. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes. Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
1426. Passes 9 to zero. Council member
Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon written record. Temporary
resolution 1426.
>> Second.
>> A motion, a second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 1426. Any discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes. Yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skoover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 1426 passes 9 to
zero.
>> Now move on to temporary resolution
1526. A resolution to authorize the
service safety director to accept Bureau
of Workers Comp Bureau of Workers
Compensation Safety Intervention Grant
funds to increase receipts, appropriate
from the unencumbered balance, and amend
the certificate of other sources and
appropriations with the county auditor
in the 0.15 levy fund 2046
and to declare an emergency. This is
through safety committee, Mr. Og and Mr.
Skunover.
>> Council member Og.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution
1526.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution 1526. Any
discussion? Council member Og.
>> Not on the suspension.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjac,
>> abstain.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Who?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
passes 8 to zero with one abstension.
Council member OG.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
the resolution temporarily numbered
1526.
>> Second motion a second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 1526.
Any discussion council member?
>> Uh last time we discussed this I didn't
ask for any uh input or opinion from uh
the fire chief Slate. And if you have
anything,
thank you, Councilman Al. Um, yes. This
piece of legislation is to authorize the
acceptance of a safety intervention
grant um that we applied for and
received for the fire department. Um,
the money, it's a matching grant to
purchase a Lucas chest compression
device. Um, and it will be put on one of
our frontline units to service the
citizens every day. Any questions?
>> Uh, so they're paying for about half,
we're paying for about the other half.
>> Correct. The the balance of every three
years, the city is eligible for up to
$40,000 in safety intervention grants.
Um, back in 2024, we applied for and
received a grant totaling 28,000. Um,
there was a balance of roughly 10,800
um for the project. Typically, the match
amount is higher. Um, but that was the
balance of our 40,000 for our three-year
cycle. Uh, so we've been very fortunate
to have these funds available to us to
help supplement the cost of this
important equipment um to serve the
citizens and we'll hope to um get more
support and approval for future
projects.
>> This ends the
three years and then we'll have another
three years application coming up next
year.
I I would have to double check to see
when that cycle does begin again. Um but
yes, [clears throat] it does um there
will be a three-year cycle that
restarts. Um in the past, you know, we
can go back uh many years and talk about
other equipment that we've got. So, it's
been um a very useful grant for the the
fire department and the city as a whole.
>> Thank you.
>> Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Cohen.
>> You still have to call Mr.
>> Mr. Bisjac.
>> Abstain.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Nisley.
>> Mr. OG.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> M. Smiley.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. Sully?
>> Sorry. Temp.
>> Temporary resolution 1526 passes 8 to
zero with one abstension. Temporary
resolution 1626.
a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into grant
agreements and to enter into contracts
contracts with various consultants for
the project known as the east side
industrial connector project. Mr. Public
Works Committee, Mr. Carr and Miss
Smiley,
>> Council Member Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of resolution
temporarily numbered 16-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 1626.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Um, city engineer Kurt Shon spoke to
this last meeting. Um, unless there are
questions, I have nothing further to
add.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr.
Yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
1626 passes 9 to zero. Council member
Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council or that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
resolution temporarily numbered 16-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 1626. Any further
discussion?
>> Well, my comments were premature on the
uh last note, so
>> we got it.
>> You got it. Nothing else to say.
>> All right. Great. Anybody else?
>> All right. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 1626 passes 9 to
zero. Temporary resolution 17-26,
>> a resolution to increase receipts,
appropriate from the unencumber balance,
and amend the certificate with the
county auditor in the wastewater
replacement and improvement fund 6023
and to issue that announce certificates
for the payments of bills. Mr. Dwater,
water pollution control committee, Mr.
Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. And I move
that council suspend its rules and wave
uh the third reading for resolutions
temp or for temporary resolutions 17-26,
18-26, and 19-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third readings of
temporary resolutions 1726, 1826, 1926.
Any discussion on the motions to
suspend?
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolutions
1726, 1826, and 1926. Passes 9 to zero.
Council member Bisjack,
>> I have nothing.
>> We need a motion.
>> Oh, I'm I apologize. All right. I I move
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 17-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 1726. Any further
discussion?
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoo,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass. Engross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
1726 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
resolution 1826.
A resolution to amend the certificate
with the county auditor appropriate from
the unencumbered balance. Increase
receipts and complete a fund to fund
transfer in the wastewater fund 6004 and
in the wastewater utility reserve fund
629.
This is through water water pollution
control committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss
Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass engross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
18-26.
>> Second.
>> A motion and a second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 1826. Any
discussion?
>> No, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Miss Cohen?
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. H?
>> Yes. Mr. Nicely?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. OG? Yes,
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Miss Smiley.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. Sully.
>> Motion to pass and address and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 1826 passes 9 to zero.
Temporary resolution 19-26.
A resolution to appropriate
[clears throat] from the unencumbered
balance and amend the certificate of
appropriations with the county auditor
in the wastewater replacement and
improvement fund 6023 and to authorize
the issuance of then and now
certificates for payment of bills. This
is again through water water pollution
control committee Mr. Bisjack and Miss
Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
19-26.
Second.
>> A motion and second to pass a gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 1926. Any discussion? Council
member Bisch.
>> No. Mr. President,
>> please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
Motion to pass engross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
1926 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
resolution 20-26
>> a resolution authorizing the service
safety director to enter into a contract
with EMT for design services and
appropriate from unencumbered balance
and amend the certificate of
appropriations with the county auditor
and the parks and recreation fund 2012.
This is through service committee. Mr.
Nisley and Mr. Hoop.
>> Council member Nisley.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of temporary
resolution number 20-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading
[clears throat] of temporary resolution
20-26.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Not on the motion to suspend.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunberg,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
20-26
passes 9 to zero.
>> Council member Nisley.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
number 20-26.
>> Second. We have a motion in a second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
20-26.
Any discussion? Council member Nisley.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. President. This
resolution is just to authorize the uh
the contract for with M and M&H&T for
design services to help uh phase one of
Miller Park redevelopment with the for
through the parks department.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the RO.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
20-26 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
resolution 23-26.
>> A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumber balance.
Amend the certificate with the county
auditor in the 045 police fire and levy
fund [snorts] 2047 for CPT state grant
reimbursement. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This is the
second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 2326.
That concludes Well, wait. We've got
first readings tonight. There we go.
>> Concludes second readings.
>> All right. Well, I think it might be
good for a moment to just say that we're
moving into first readings now. These
are pieces of legislation that have now
since been introduced since we had that
break [snorts] because of the snowstorm.
You're going to see that those mostly
are going to go for three readings um
because we had to move some of those up
and you won't see as many um emergency
pieces and motions to suspend. So, uh,
we'll begin tonight with, uh, temporary
resolution 2526,
>> a resolution to authorize all actions
necessary to accept a Northeast Ohio
Public Emergency Council 202 or 2026
Energized Community Grant. It's through
finance committee. Mr. Skunover, Mr.
Als,
>> Council Member Skunover.
>> Uh, first of three readings, please.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 2526. And now to hold me
wrong is temporary resolution 2626.
>> A resolution to authorize that announce
certificates for the payment of bills in
the water water revenue fund 6003 and to
declare an emergency. Mr. through water
water pollution control committee. Um
Mr. Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you Mr. President. I move that
council suspend its rules and wave the
second and third reading for temporary
resolutions 26-26 and 29-26.
>> Second.
Have a motion in the second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
readings of temporary resolution 2626
and temporary resolution 2926. Any
discussion on the motion to suspend
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skoover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> Mr. Si.
>> Yes.
>> Is that it?
>> That's it. Yeah.
>> Sorry. Okay. Motion to suspend the rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary resolution 2626 and 2926.
Passes 9 to zero. Council member
Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
26-26.
>> Second. We have a motion to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution 2626. Any
discussion?
>> No. Thank you, Mr. President.
>> Please call the RO.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Smiley or Miss Smiley, I'm so sorry.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. Sully?
>> Temporary resolution 2626 passes 9 to
zero. Temporary resolution 2726.
A resolution to increase and and
decrease appropriations in the water
revenue fund 6003 to cover a shortfall
in the retirement benefits account. M is
through water water pollution control
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This is the
first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 2726.
Temporary resolution 2826. A resolution
to authorize the service safety director
to enter into a contract for the
construction of the Frederick Street
sewer separation project. This is
through water water pollution control
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. Once again,
this is the first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 2826.
Temporary resolution 2926. A resolution
to authorize the mayor to prepare and
submit an application to receive
technical design and/or funding
assistance from the National Resource
Conservation Conservation Service, NRCS,
for the planning and design and/or
construction of the stream bank
stabilization restoration project to
protect sanitary sewer system
infrastructure to execute contracts,
agreements or agree agreements as
required and to declare an emergency.
Again, this is through water water
pollution control committee. This is Mr.
Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
29-26.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution 29-26.
Any discussion? Council member Bisjack.
>> No, Mr. President,
>> please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes. Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Motion to pass, engross, and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
29-26
passes 9 to zero. Temporary resolution
30-26. A resolution to authorize a then
announced certificate for payment in an
of an A electric bill for street
lighting in the general fund 10001 and
to declare an emergency. This through
finance committee Mr. Skunover and Mr.
Sully
>> council member Skooner over
>> first of three readings please. First of
three or first of two?
>> Two, I'm sorry.
>> First of two readings.
>> First of two readings on temporary
resolution 30-26.
Temporary resolution 31-26.
>> A resolution to increase and decrease
appropriations in the general fund to
cover a uniform allowance for recent
promotion within the Lancaster Fire
Department and to declare an emergency.
Mr. Safety Committee, Mr. Bisjack and
Mr. Al.
>> Council member Bisjack. Thank you, Mr.
President. This is the first of three
readings. First of three readings on
temporary resolution 3126.
We have now reached the end of the
reading of resolutions and we move to
reading of ordinances. There are no
third readings this evening. We will
move to second reading beginning with
temporary ordinance 2-26.
an ordinance to authorize the mayor to
acquire permanent and temporary rideway
as necessary for the Memorial Pierce
Whittier new sidewalks projects known as
the FAI-C33
MR70505-4.93.09
project. This is through public works
committee Mr. Carr and Mr. Bishjack.
>> Council member Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of ordinance
temporarily number 2-26.
>> Second. We have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance 2-26. Any
discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Not to the suspension.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Miss Cohen?
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop?
>> Mr. Nisley?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. OG?
>> Mr. Skunover? Yes.
>> Miss Smiley.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. Sully.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
2-26 passes 9 to zero. Council member
Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record ordinance
temporarily numbered 2-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
uh temporary ordinance 2-26. Council
member Carr. Um once again this is for
the the right of right of way for
sidewalk work in that in the morier
area. Um no further comments other than
uh what city engineer addressed last
meeting.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Miss Cohen.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes. Mr. Nisley.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Og.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Smiley.
>> And Mr. Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary ordinance
2-26 passes 9 to zero. We now move on to
first reading beginning with temporary
ordinance 4-26.
>> An ordin ordinance authorizing the mayor
to grant four permanent supplemental
easements to the Ohio Power Company
necessary for the construction and
maintenance of electric facilities and
to declare an emergency. It's through
law committee. Miss Smiley and Mr. Carr.
>> Council member Smiley.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. First of
three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 4-26.
That concludes the reading of ordinances
this evening. We now move on to tabled
legislation, which um there is none
unfinished business. Does anybody have
any unfinished business this evening?
Thank you. We'll now move on to new
business. Um and we would recognize
Mayor McDaniel.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I thought
since we had five new council people,
I'd take an opportunity to explain
um the number of boards and commissions
that we have and um how they work
differently depending on what what
commission board or committee you're on.
But so we have 15
um boards, commissions or committees and
all these uh allow our citizens to
participate in city government in
various ways. uh some are
decision-making boards, some are
advisory, some are committees that
review information the city gathers
throughout the year on various projects,
etc., etc. In the audience right here, I
see a board of park commissioner, a
member, uh planning commission member,
um two BZA members, board of zoning
appeals, and a civil service
commissioner
here tonight listening to what's going
on in the city. Uh these people have all
volunteered their time to serve on these
uh boards or commissions and it's
greatly appreciated. Uh tonight
I have the uh duty by the revised code
to uh appoint uh individuals to the tree
commission. Let me tell you about our
tree commission. Our tree commission has
a mission statement as follows. planting
today for tomorrow to maximize the
economic, environmental, and social
benefit benefits of a sustainable urban
forest for the residents of the city of
Lancaster. That's their mission. That's
their assignment. These are all
volunteers, but this is actually an
advisory board that works with the
safety service director and our arborist
who are also voting members of this
particular uh board. So, we have seven
members. Five are nominated by the mayor
and then approved by council and two are
assigned by ordinance 93902 and that is
the SSD and the city arborous or the
parks and wreck director.
So tonight I am recommending the
reappoint of David Bert. He's a longtime
chair of the tree commission. Uh serve
this city well and is agreeing to serve
going forward.
Mike Zawistla. Mike is a second fullterm
member, but Mike also brings it's what
he does for a living. He knows trees. He
literally lives and breathes trees and
cares about the tree canopy in the city
of Lancaster. And if you haven't talked
to Mike, you'd see his passion if you
did. And finally, uh, Ron Harvey
has, uh, opted not to be reappointed,
and he made a recommendation that I
appoint Michaela Tusing to that vacant
position. And I reached out to Michaela,
and she's, uh, agreed to serve. Uh,
again, these are all volunteers who are
stepping forward to assist the city and
uh, a board where we are required by law
to have in place. These are four-year
terms.
Um,
you should have all received Michaela's
resume outlining her background, but
what really is most important in the
background is a passion for this city
and a desire to serve. And she brings
both of those to this position. And I
strongly recommend the appointment of
Michaela, Mike, and David Bert uh to the
tree commission so they can continue and
in Michaela's case start serving the
city.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mr. Mayor, do we have a
motion to appoint uh the listed
individuals to the tree commission?
>> Yes, Mr. President that motion.
>> I'll second it. We have a motion in a
second to appoint Mr. Brit. And how do
you say, Mr.
>> Zistla? Zawistla.
>> And I'm sure that's incorrect, but
that's how it's spelled.
>> Okay, we're going with it. We You know
who you are.
>> I'm close.
>> Um and um Miss Tussing to the tree
commission. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
We welcome them all and we thank them
for their service. We know that uh
serving on a commission uh whether it be
one that is um making recommendations or
making decisions is tough because you
take time away from uh your regular
lives and your family. So, we thank you
for uh doing that work. Announcement of
scheduled meetings. I have um next
regular sessions of council March 9th,
2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in council
chambers and then again on March 23rd,
2026 at 6:30 p.m. and here in council
chambers.
>> We have no special scheduled meetings.
Now we would announce the regularly
scheduled committee meetings.
>> I have safety committee meeting April
3rd, 2026 at 8 a.m. 1897 conference room
in the city hall. Water water pollution
control committee April 10th 2026 at
7:30 a.m. 1897 conference room in city
hall. I have a bet basically nobody
wanted to do anything in March. So law
committee meeting April 17th, 2026 at
12:30 p.m. 1897 conference room in city
hall. And then finally, um, economic
development committee meeting, April
30th, 2026 at 7:30 a.m. in 1897,
conference room, city hall.
>> Thank you. Um, reading of bills. I have
one for $18 or I'm sorry, reverse those
I $82.74 cents for publications of re
resolutions um permanent ordinance 1-26
and permanent ordinance 2-26.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we pay the bill. Second.
>> A motion and second to pay the bill. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. Um,
next meeting which will be on March 9th
in new business, we will seek any
committee updates from council members.
We'll go back and I know people are just
getting in the swing of things. That's
why we dispensed with it tonight, but
that next meeting we will be looking for
that. Uh, we've also received a request
um to have a presentation related to
um refresh me uh service safety director
related to trees. I know that. Yes,
it'll be uh Mr. Gayfield, if he's still
here, it will be Mr. Gayfield uh from
the parks department doing a a
presentation on trees in April related
to Arbor Day. Yes,
>> correct. Okay. So, that will be our
first meeting in April. So, if we could
mark that down as well.
>> We have no need for an executive
session. Therefore, I will take a motion
to adjurnn.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to adjurnn.
All those in favor signify by saying I.
>> I. We are adjourned. Please remember to
sign your legislation before you leave
this evening. Hope you don't get any
cramps cuz you're going to have to sign.
>> Oh my god.
The Frankie [music] Smith Funeral Home
and Crematory in Lancaster and the
Johnson Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore
have a long and wonderful history of
[music] serving our community. Feel free
to give us a call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see [music] us at either of
our two locations, 405 North Columbus
Street in Lancaster and 207 South Main
Street in Baltimore. Respect for
tradition, regard [music] for change.
Great automotive service is just around
the corner at the Buckeye family of
dealerships. Whether it's Buckeye Nissan
at Hillyard, Georgeesville Nissan
[music] at the Georgeesville Auto Mall,
Buckeye Honda of Lancaster, Buckeye
Toyota of Lancaster, or Buckeye
Collision Center in Hillyard. Team
Buckeye services all makes and models at
each location utilizing [music] modern
practices with hundreds of years of
experience, giving you peace of mind.
That's how we Buckeye. [music]